Elmina R. Lucke Papers, 1897-1987
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
Elmina Rose Lucke papers
1897-1987
Lucke, Elmina Rose
MS 192
5 boxes (4.5 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Professor of social work and social studies, founder and director of the Dehli School of Social Work, consultant for social work education, and YWCA official. The Elmina Lucke papers focus on her work abroad as educator, administrator, and consultant for social work. Materials include correspondence with former students and associates in Egypt, India, and Pakistan; photographs of her travels; speeches; writings, including an unpublished memoir; and a transcript and tapes of an oral history.
1889 Born on December 6 in Carleton, Michigan
1896 Attended one-room school in Carleton.
1908 Graduated from high school in Toledo, Ohio.
1912-1913 Helped establish and taught in Carleton's first high school.
1912 Graduated from Oberlin College, Phi Beta Kappa.
1913-1914 Studied at the University of Berlin, returning home because of outbreak of war.
1914-1917 Taught history at Scott High School in Toledo.
1917-1919 Worked for the U.S. Children's Bureau in Gary, Indiana, directing social services; studied social service at the University of Chicago. Employed by the U.S. Bureau of Labor Statistics to conduct surveys in Oklahoma and Kansas.
1919-1923 Founded and directed the International Institute in Detroit, established by the Y.W.C.A. for recent immigrants.
1923-1926 Taught history and served on committee on curriculum reorganization for Toledo high schools.
1926-1927 Enrolled in International Law and Relations doctoral program at Columbia University as one of first two women to enter this program; received M.A.
1927-1946 Taught social studies at Lincoln School, Teacher's College, Columbia University, and was an associate in research.
1930-1931 Traveled around the world studying social science teaching with a grant from the American Historical Association.
1937-1969 Served on the National Board of the American Council of Nationalities Service.
1946-1949 Founded and directed the Delhi School of Social Work under the auspices of the Y.W.C.A. in India.
1950-1951 Awarded Fulbright Scholarship to Cairo, where she served as consultant in social work training to the Cairo School of Social Work and as advisor to the U.S. Point IV program. Worked as consultant for the American Council of Voluntary Agencies for Foreign Service.
1952-1955 Appointed chairman of the United Nations Technical Assistance Program to Pakistan advising on social work education.
1955 Appointed to Board of Trustees, New Lincoln School.
1956 Received Doctor of Humane Letters degree from Oberlin College. Appointed to Advisory Board, Adelphi School of Social Work.
1959 Appointed as its representative to the United Nations by the International Federation of University Women.
1960 Served on Alumni Board of Oberlin College.
1964-1965 Served as delegate, Tonga Conference, Pan-Pacific and Southeast Asia Women's Association (PPSEAWA), and U.N. consultant, Australian Council of Women.
1965 Appointed as its representative to the United Nations by the PPSEAWA; presented proposals relating to women's issues for the PPSEAWA at the U.N. Conference on Women in Teheran.
1975 Member, Virginia Gildersleeve International Fund for University Women, Inc
1981 Named, "Citizen of the Day," September 16, in Sarasota, Florida.
1983 Received Gwendolyn S. Cherry Award from AAUW Miami Branch for contributions in the field of women's rights.
1985 Publication of Unforgettable Memories, A Collection of Letters in India.
1986 Nominated for the Michigan Women's Hall of Fame.
1987 Died on October 3l in Sarasota, Florida
The papers are concentrated in the period after World War II. There are some items, mainly from the 1930s, relating to her family, teaching, and research. With the exception of family letters and photographs, the papers document her professional work and are not personal in nature.
This collection is organized into five series:
I. Correspondence
II. Professional Activities
III. Writings and Speeches
IV. Biographical Materials and Memorabilia
V. Photographs
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The collection is open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection without any additional restrictions.
Additional Formats
Selections from the Elmina Lucke Papers can be viewed in the Web exhibit "An Ever-Widening Circle of Friendship": YWCA Overseas Secretaries from China to Liberia.
History of the Collection
The papers are a gift from Elmina Lucke. The first installment was received in February 1986 and additional materials have been received since then. After Ms. Lucke decided to place her papers in the Sophia Smith Collection, the Schlesinger Library transferred the portion of her memoir that had been on deposit there. Donations of correspondence and photographs have been received from Ross Lucke, Marilyn Brooks, and Marjorie Creelman.
Search Terms
Graduate School of Social Work. University of Dehli--History--Sources; Pan-Pacific and Southeast Asia Women's Association--History--Sources; Social service--Developing countries--History--Sources; Social work education--Egypt--History--Sources; Social work education--India--History--Sources; Social work education--United States--History--Sources; Social workers--United States--History--Sources; Social workers--India--History--Sources; Young Women's Christian Association of the U.S.A.--History; Young Women's Christian Associations--India--History; Lucke, Elmina Rose; India--Social conditions--20th century--Sources; Social sciences--Study and teaching (Higher)--United States; South Asia--Social conditions--20th century--Sources
- Series I. CORRESPONDENCE
  This series consists of two sections, General and Family. Other letters are filed according to subject in other series.
  General correspondence is arranged in alphabetical order. A large number of letters from former students in Egypt, India, and Pakistan provide a view of social work in these countries. Other correspondents whose letters are of special interest are Madhav Gore, principal of the Delhi School of Social Work from 1953 to 1962, who has corresponded with Miss Lucke for more than thirty years about the school's development and about social work in India; Talitha Gerlach, employee of the Y.W.C.A. and the China Welfare Institute in Shanghai, who has written to Miss Lucke since the end of World War II; and Ruth Rickover, wife of a U.S. naval officer stationed in China, whose letters describe events at the time of the Japanese invasion of China in 1938.
  There are copies of letters by Elmina Lucke to the Gore family and to former students at the end of this section.
  Family correspondence consists of letters from Miss Lucke written while traveling abroad. They contain detailed descriptions of places she visited and people she met and are also expressive of her closeness to her family. There are also letters from various family members.
- Series II. PROFESSIONAL ACTIVITIES
  This series consists of ten sections which document Elmina Lucke's long career as an educator, researcher, administrator, and consultant. These materials are concentrated on her work abroad from 1930 to 1968. There is no documentation of her earliest work in high school teaching, for the Children's Bureau, and as founder and director of the International Institute of Detroit, but Miss Lucke recalls some of those experiences in her oral history.
  The Investigation of the Social Studies in the Schools section contains papers from a trip Miss Lucke took in l930-3l with a grant from the American Historical Association which had undertaken this investigation in l929. There is correspondence, reports about educational systems in some of the countries she visited, printed materials, and miscellaneous papers. Reminiscences about this trip may be found in Series III.
  The Lincoln School section contains a variety of materials about Miss Lucke's twenty-year association with the school. Documents include correspondence, research notes, clippings, publications, a bibliography, and two drafts of social studies curricula for high schools. Letters of her former Lincoln students, including David Rockefeller, are in Series I.
  The Delhi School of Social Work section contains correspondence, reports, publications, and a variety of printed materials produced by the school, established under the auspices of the Y.W.C.A. in 1946. There are documents and published accounts about her work as the founder and director of the school. There are papers and correspondence from Miss Lucke's trips to Assam and Burma pertaining to social work education in those countries. There are publications, reports, and correspondence received by Miss Lucke after she left the school.
  The Cairo School of Social Work section contains correspondence, notes and texts for three lectures, reports, planning documents, and other papers relating to Miss Lucke's work as a consultant on social work education in Egypt as a Fulbright fellow.
  The American Council of Voluntary Agencies for Foreign Service section consists of two reports relating to Miss Lucke's tenure as director of a committee studying the distribution of voluntary foreign aid in the years from 1946 to 1952.
  The United Nations Technical Assistance Program, Pakistan section contains Elmina Lucke's published report about this program, correspondence, research notes and interviews, a report by Julia Henderson, materials relating to the first training course for social workers, and miscellaneous papers and printed materials.
  The University of Michigan, Community Development Seminar section contains a report summarizing discussions and class lists for seminars taught by Elmina Lucke during the summers of 1958 and 1962.
  The International Federation of University Women and the Pan-Pacific and Southeast Asia Women's Association sections contain reports, correspondence, proceedings, and other papers documenting Elmina Lucke's work as representative of these organizations to the United Nations.
  The Other Professional Associations and Activities section consists of correspondence and printed materials from various organizations.
- Series III. WRITINGS AND SPEECHES
  This series consists of separate sections of unpublished and published work. The Unpublished section contains her memoir, "Remembering at Eighty-Eight, Letters I Should have Written." These reminiscences begin with an around-the-world trip in 1930 and describe Miss Lucke's impressions and work abroad through her last trip in 1969. It was published shortly before her death in l987. There are also some texts and notes for speeches in this section. A few writings and speeches are filed in Series II. The Published section contains the book, Unforgettable Memories, published in India in 1985, which is a portion of her memoir. There are also copies of a number of articles written by her.
- Series IV. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS AND MEMORABILIA
  This series consists of two sections. The Biographical Materials section contains chronologies highlighting Elmina Lucke's career, numerous clippings about her from 1931 to 1987, and documents concerning several honors she received. The Memorabilia section includes mementos from the 1930-31 trip and a book about the trip by her traveling companion.
- Series V. PHOTOGRAPHS
  This series contains photographs of Elmina Lucke, her friends, and family. There are also photographs from her travels, mainly in India and the Far East. Among the oldest items in this collection are copies of pictures from a family album, dating probably from 1897.
- Series I. CORRESPONDENCE
  - General
    - A-Al, 1959-86 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - An-Aw, 1949-77, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Bai-Bau, 1950-77 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Be-Bl, 1950-51, 1974, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Br, 1950-85 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Ca-Ch, 1931-76 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Cl-Cr, 1957-79 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Creelman, Marjorie B., 1945, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - D, 1946-76 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - E, 1931, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - F, 1963-85 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - G, 1949-81 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Gerlach, Talitha, 1947-84 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Gore, Madhav, 1950-78, l986 (Box 1, Folder 14-17)
    - Gore, Phyllis, 1956-83 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Gore, Vikas and Nirmala, 1965-80 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Gwyer, Maurice, 1950-52 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - H, 1925-87 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Harvey, Constance H., 1930, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Hyslop, Beatrice, 1955-56, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - I, J, 1924, 1955-85 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Khan, Kaniz S., 1954-87, undated (Box 1, Folder 26-27)
    - Khan, Raiana Lia Ali, 1962-85 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Khan, Mustafa Ali, 1956-82 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - L, 1949-87, undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Lincoln School Class of 1938 reunions, 1978-79, undated (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Mac-Mayer, 1950-84 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Me, 1949-77 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Mi-Mu, 1949-85 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Moses, Dorothy, 1951-80 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - N, 1951-84 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Omer, Salima, 1957, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Pa, 1929-78 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Pe-Pu, 1934-85 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Q, 1959-72 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - R, 1931-86 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Rickover, Ruth and George, 1935-38 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Rockefeller, David, 1932-45 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Sa-Se, 1949-86 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Sh-Si, 1949-79 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Sm, 1966-85 (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - St-Sw, 1932-77 (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - Stanford, Peter, 1944-84 (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - T, 1954-81 (Box 1, Folder 49)
    - Thorson, Maxine, 1974-85 (Box 1, Folder 50)
    - Toll, Anna-Ma, 1956-83 (Box 1, Folder 51)
    - U-V, 1949-86 (Box 1, Folder 52)
    - Valadian, Margaret, 1972-86 (Box 1, Folder 53)
    - W, 1933, 1949, 1956-85 (Box 1, Folder 54)
    - Wiser, Charlotte and Bill, 1956-72 (Box 1, Folder 55)
    - Youngblood, Eileen, 1955-71 (Box 1, Folder 56)
    - Zaki, S.M., 1955 (Box 1, Folder 57)
    - Lucke, Elmina R. (to various correspondents), 1899, 1959-84, undated (Box 1, Folder 58-59)
    - Christmas cards, undated (Box 1, Folder 60-63)
    - Unidentified, 1931-85, undated (Box 1, Folder 64-69)
  - Family (from Elmina R. Lucke)
    - Europe, 19l3, l925-30 (Box 1, Folder 69a-71)
    - Russia, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 72)
    - Middle East, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 73)
    - India, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 74)
    - Southeast Asia, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 75-76)
    - China, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 77)
    - Japan, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 78-79)
    - Mexico, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 80)
    - Europe, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 81)
    - Egypt, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 82)
    - India, Burma, 1946-47 (Box 1, Folder 83)
    - Miscellaneous, 1931, 1939, undated (Box 1, Folder 84)
  - Family (to Elmina R. Lucke)
    - Brooks, 1954, 1969-75, undated (Box 1, Folder 85)
    - Nickerson, 1966-71, undated (Box 1, Folder 86)
    - Others, 1949, 1975-76, undated (Box 1, Folder 87)
- Series II. PROFESSIONAL ACTIVITIES
  - Investigation of the Social Studies in the Schools
    - All-India Women's Conference, Lahore: printed materials, 1931 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence and itinerary, 1930 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Educational systems abroad: notes, 1930-31 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - "Instruction in History in the Workers' Faculties of the U.S.S.R.": typescript, notes, charts, 1931 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - "Java": typescript, 1931 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - "Teaching of the Social Sciences. Report on India": typescript and holograph copy, 1931 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Miscellaneous papers and printed materials, 1930, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Lincoln School
    - "Asiatic Studies for Senior High Schools" c. 1944 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Bibliography for Teachers of Social Studies and Foreign Languages in Senior High Schools, 1934 Jul (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence and address list, 1934, 1947-49 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Printed matter re: field study, 1938-40 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Research notes, 1940, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - "The World from Senior High School Windows--and Doors", 1940s (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Miscellaneous printed materials, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Delhi School of Social Work
    - Application and evaluation forms, examinations, and miscellaneous papers, 1947, undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Articles about the school, 1949, undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Book lists, 1946, undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Correspondence
      - General, 1945-80 (Box 2, Folder 18-23)
      - Topical
        - Assam, including itineraries and reports, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 24)
        - Burma, 1948-50 (Box 2, Folder 25)
        - Delhi School of Social Work Society, 1976-82 (Box 2, Folder 26)
        - Letters of introduction, 1946-47, undated (Box 2, Folder 27)
        - Y.W.C.A. of India (Ivy Khan), 1965-79 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Fund raising sources: annotated lists, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Moses, Dorothy, "Village Life and Social Work," The Survey, 1952 May (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - National Y.W.C.A. of India, Burma, and Ceylon: meeting agenda, list of council members, 1947, undated (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Publications: bulletins, annual reports, brochures, pamphlets, 1948-57 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Publicity: printed materials, interview, correspondence, press releases, 1949-51, undated (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Reports by Dorothy Moses, Edward Lindeman, and others, 1947-59 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Reports by Elmina R.Lucke, 1947-51 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - "Social Service Training Project, India: preparations, interviews in the U.S.": notebook contents, 1946-47 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Syllabi and prospectuses, 1946-62, undated (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Miscellaneous notes, printed materials, clipping, 1947-64 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Cairo School of Social Work
    - Background notes for lectures, 1950-51 (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Correspondence, 1950-51 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Form letters from Elmina R. Lucke, 1950-51 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Fulbright award: correspondence, printed materials, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - Reports and planning documents, 1950-51 (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - Staff questionnaire: form, report, tabulations, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - "Three Lectures on Community Organization": text, correspondence, clipping, press release, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - Printed materials and appointment book, 1950, undated (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - American Council of Volunteer Agencies for Foreign Service
    - The Role of Voluntary Agencies in Technical Assistance, and an incomplete report, pages 20-37, 1953, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence and printed materials, 1978-80 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - United Nations Technical Assistance Program, Pakistan
    - "First Training Course for Social Workers": lists of students and teachers, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - General correspondence, 1952-79 (Box 3, Folder 4-6)
    - Henderson, Julia: reports and correspondence, 1953-60 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Lucke, Elmina R.: reports, research notes, and interviews, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 8-10)
    - Miscellaneous papers and printed materials, 1953-54, undated (Box 3, Folder 11-12)
    - Pakistan Association of Social Workers: correspondence and printed materials, 1955-62 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Social Welfare Project, United Nations Technical Assistance Programme: published text, correspondence, draft, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - University of Michigan, Community Development Seminar
    - Class lists, book list, 1958-62 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - "Community Development in Newly Developing Countries": report, 1958 Aug (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - International Federation of University Women
    - U.N. Economic and Social Council: reports, 1959-61 (Box 3, Folder 17-18)
    - Miscellaneous, 1939, 1961,1964 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Pan-Pacific and Southeast Asia Women's Association
    - Conference agenda proposal and by-laws, c. 1961
      - Eleventh Conference, Hawaii, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 20)
      - "Problems Arising from the Growing Population of the World": proceedings, 1968 Aug 12-23 (Box 3, Folder 21)
      - Reports and correspondence, 1967-69 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - General correspondence, 1954, 1961-66 (Box 3, Folder 23-24)
    - Tenth Conference, Tonga, 1964
      - Correspondence, 1964, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 25)
      - Notes of Elmina R. Lucke, 1959-64, undated (Box 3, Folder 26)
      - Printed materials, clippings, 1962-64, undated (Box 3, Folder 27)
      - "The Role of Women in Preserving the Cultural Heritage of Mankind": proceedings, 1964 Aug 15-27 (Box 3, Folder 28)
      - Speech by Elmina R. Lucke, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - U.N. Committee reports
      - Commission for Social Development, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 30)
      - Commission on the Status of Women, 1964-65 (Box 3, Folder 31)
      - UNESCO, 1969-73 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Other Professional Associations and Activities
    - Scott High School, fiftieth anniversary: printed materials, program, 1962-63 (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - Virginia Gildersleeve International Fund for University Women: correspondence, membership lists, minutes, brochure, 1975-84 (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - World Assembly of Youth, Singapore: invitations and programs, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - Miscellaneous correspondence and printed material, 1950-84, undated (Box 3, Folder 36-39)
- Series III. WRITINGS AND SPEECHES
  - Published Writings and Speeches
    - All-Asian Women's Conference, First Session, Lahore, 1931 Jan 19-25 (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - "An American Social Worker Abroad" Amerika, no. 51: article in Russian and an English translation, undated (Box 3, Folder 41)
    - "A Second School of Social Work for Asia," The Woman's Press, 1949 Jan (Box 3, Folder 42)
    - "Author of Indian Liberty," review of The Life of Mahatma Gandhi, The Survey: copy and draft, 1950 Sep (Box 3, Folder 43)
    - "Extending Social Services: Women Set New Goals for the New India," R oshni, Journal of the All India Women's Conference, 1948 Dec (Box 3, Folder 44)
    - "Have You Seen 'The River,'" Progressive Education, 1939 Mar (Box 3, Folder 45)
    - "New Theories in Practice," The New Era, 1930 Apr (Box 3, Folder 46)
    - "New Vocational Horizons for our Seniors," The Link, 1941 Feb (Box 3, Folder 47)
    - Unforgettable Memories: A Collection of Letters, Delhi, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 48)
    - "Who Shall be Trained in Social Work," Provincial Conference for Social Work, Madras, 1948 Jul (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - Unpublished Writings and Speeches
    - "An International Institute for Detroit," Convention of International Institutes, Detroit, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 50)
    - "Memorial for Josephine Stanton", 1981 Nov (Box 3, Folder 51)
    - "Remembering at Eighty-Eight, Letters I Should Have Written", post-1977 (Box 3, Folder 52-57)
    - Miscellaneous notes for talks, 1941-64, undated (Box 3, Folder 58-59)
- Series IV. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS AND MEMORABILIA
  - Biographical Materials
    - Oral history conducted by Jacqueline Van Voris: transcript and tapes, July 11 to 13, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 0)
    - Biographical data, 1959-87, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Lucke family: printed materials, 1952-60, undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Harbor Light, Plymouth Harbor, Sarasota: newsletter, 1970-82 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Honors
      - American Association of University Women, 1981-86 (Box 4, Folder 4)
      - Oberlin College, Doctor of Humane Letters, 1955-56 (Box 4, Folder 5)
      - Other, 1917-86 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - "Bootstraps, Bullets and Brooms," proposed article about Elmina R. Lucke by Tracy Millard: draft, correspondence, 1950-51 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Newspaper clippings about Elmina R. Lucke, 1931-86 (Box 4, Folder 8-9)
    - Book donations and gifts: correspondence, lists, 1969-83 (Box 4, Folder 10-13)
  - Memorabilia